我写给元帅的信，周一要交的。
My letter to the Maréchal. It's for Monday.
德国人因为十一月十一日加强了检查。
我碰上了一个检查站。
The Germans have strengthened their controls
for November 11th. I ran into a checkpoint.
苏珊娜，计划的前提是
你的日程不能有任何异常。
Suzanne, the plan assumed that nothing in your
schedule would differ from normal.
……老板是警方的线人。
你要是这么说，就等着进牢房吧。
... the owner is a police informer.
If you say that, you'll sleep in jail.
但如果有人看到你九点才放报纸
而不是八点，那就证明你在撒谎。
But if someone sees you leave the papers
at 9 o'clock and not 8, it'll show you're lying.
寒流
COLD SNAP
大概是因为十一月十一日
德国人加塞的东西。
Probably because of the German insert
for November 11th.
警察会问你为什么没有报告。
The Police will ask why you didn't report it.
这样的话我们有三十分钟塞传单
十分钟去锯木厂……
That leaves us 30 minutes to slip in the flyers
10 minutes to go to the sawmill...
我请了瓦格纳军士来旁听
孩子们朗读写给元帅的信。
I asked Feldwebel Wagner to be present
at the reading of letters to the Maréchal.
元帅说了要合作
那我们就合作。
The Maréchal said we need to collaborate,
so let's collaborate.
那件事确实很不幸。
但最后嘛，显然
他们把事情压下去了。
That affair was really unfortunate.
But in the end, obviously,
they pigeon-holed the thing.
法兰西国家通过我的口……
L'Etat Francaise expresses itself through me...
这些毯子和这些汤
是由省政府提供，并得到……
These blankets, and this soup which are offered
by the Sous-Préfecture and with the assistance...
这些毯子，这些汤
是复兴的温暖……
These blankets, and this soup,
are the warmth of renewal...
在那位可敬的
凡尔登光荣胜利者的领导下。
Under the leadership of the
venerable and glorious victor of Verdun.
法国人就是一群吃货。
The French are really just bellies.
你们必须阻止
十一月十一日的任何爱国示威活动。
You must prevent any
patriotic demonstrations on November 11th.
放心。人们吃饱了
就不会闹事了。
Don't worry. When people are satisfied,
they don't think.
您怕死人游行吗？
You're afraid the dead will demonstrate ?
……但和我父亲一样，我是军人
我服从命令。
... but like my father, I'm a soldier
and I carry out orders.
我以为蒙图瓦会面之后
会为战俘们做些努力的。
I thought that after Montoire,
an effort would have been made for the POWs.
是啊，当然不用。
但事到如今，必须做了。
No, of course not.
But in the end, yes. In fact right now.
富尔基耶虽然讨厌，但他不傻。
Foulquier is a creep, but he's not an idiot.
真正的法兰西
已经摆脱了她的坏习惯……
The real France freed of her bad habits...
……和那些靠她发财的寄生虫。
...and the parasites who got rich on her back.
我找到了这张跨区明信片。
I found this Interzonal Postcard.
1940年11月11日
德国人滚出去！
11th of November 1940
OUT WITH THE GERMANS !
德国、合作、
国民革命。没有吗？
从来没有？
Germany, Collaboration,
the National Revolution.  No ?
Never ?
先生，我们按照官方指导纲要教学。
教育部什么都没发给我们。
Monsieur, we follow the Official Guidelines.
The Academy has sent us nothing.
你们应该走在官方纲要前面。
You must anticipate the Official Guidelines.
今天的问题不是找巧克力
而是改造法兰西……
Today's problem is not finding chocolate,
it's to reform France...
像每天晚上一样，塞约尔仓库
从四点到六点无人看管。
As on every night, the Sayolle depot
was unsupervised from 4 to 6.
等一下。这可不是
小孩子在电影院里吹口哨那种事。
Hang on. We're a long way from
kids whistling in a cinema, here.
没错，这更严重。这些人
是直接反对元帅的。
Exactly, it's worse. These are people
directly opposed to the Maréchal.
自从蒙图瓦会面之后
这就是一回事了。振作点。
Since Montoire it's the same thing.
Come on, pull yourself together.
她丈夫1936年加入过工人国际法国支部。
Her husband was in the SFIO in 1936.
要策划这样一次行动
首先需要构思，然后组织。
To mount a such a coup it first
had to be conceived, then organised.
"德国人滚出去！"
这可不是党的路线。
'Germans Out !' is not really the Party Line.
但我有充分的理由相信
今年一月他在施瓦茨锯木厂成立了一个党支部。
But I've every reason to believe that last January
he formed a Party cell in the Schwartz sawmill.
马尔凯蒂说得对。只有表明
法律面前人人平等，才能赢得民心。
Marchetti's right. It's in showing that Order rules
without exception, that we'll carry people with us.
……如果德国士兵在德国
而我们的士兵在家里
那就更好了……
...be even better if the
German soldiers were in Germany,
and our soldiers were here at home....
德国士兵在法国很开心。
The German soldiers are very happy to be in France.
党不能卷入一场挑衅行动。
The Party can't be involved in a provocation.
我要你把那个贱人赶走。
I want you to get rid of that slut.
太好了。那我们肯定
能找到烟头了。
This is great. So we'll certainly
find the butt, then.
她认罪了？
没有。出人意料的是她认可了
莫尔旺迪厄夫人的证词。
She confessed ?
No. Remarkably she agreed with
the testimony of Madame Morvandieu.
也许正因如此他们才赢了战争。
That may be why they've won the war.
我不想损害她的名声。
她是个那么好的女人……
I don't want to harm her reputation.
She's such a good woman...
掠夺者偷印刷机
倒也挺奇怪的，对吧？
Funny booty for a looter, right ?
施瓦茨先生，四天前你已经
在你员工萨拉的事上骗过我一次了。
Monsieur Schwartz, you already lied to me
four days ago about your employee, Sarah.
你知道，拉尔歇先生是个老黄牛。
他不说话，埋头干活。
You know, Mr. Larcher is a work-horse.
He says nothing, he does his work.
绞索在收紧了，马塞尔。
The noose is tightening, Marcel.
别把我当傻瓜了。
Stop taking me for an mug.
如果是我负责调查
就不会有找到罪犯的风险了。
If it was me in charge of the investigation,
there'd be no risk of finding culprit.
我是个蠢货。我不该公开表示
反对蒙图瓦会面和合作政策。
I'm a fool. I should never have made my
disapproval of Montoire and Collaboration plain.
呵，现在这年头真诚跟愚蠢是一回事。
Well nowadays that's the same thing.
去他的规定。
Screw the rules.
我要出一趟远门，居斯塔夫。很长时间。
I have to go on a trip, Gustave. For a long time.
听着。我有重要的事要跟你说。
没有多少时间了。
Listen. I have something important
to tell you. And there's not much time.
马塞尔，你知不知道
我必须向警方报告你的来访？
Marcel, do you realize that I'll
have to report your visit to the police ?
我只不过让你做你该做的事
你就给我上道德课！
I just ask you to do what you have to
and you give me a morality lesson !
对不起，亲爱的。
I'm sorry, love.
我勾引这个女人做我的情妇
是为了利用邮局做这次行动。
I made this woman my mistress so
I could do this action with the Post.
我们以为是政治
结果是通奸。
We were thinking of politics
and it was adultery.
听着，你们想怎么处置我都行
但别败坏她的名声。
Listen, do with me what you want,
but don't dirty her reputation.
一个战俘的妻子，通奸
这很严重。
A POW's wife, adultery, this is serious.
好。我们会暂时拘押你们两个……
Good. We'll remand both of you...
你以前从来没叫过我宝贝。
You never called me darling before.
你兄弟的事我真的很抱歉
但对他的指控证据确凿。
I'm really sorry for this situation, but the
charges against your brother are overwhelming.
……根据1939年的法律，然后……
.. under the law of 1939, and then...
法官相信了通奸的说法。
The judge swallowed the story of adultery.